A Guide to the Papers of John Powell, 1888-1978, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Powell
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7284, 7284-a
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was received in two groups as a deposit through Dr. Ernest C. Mead, of Charlottesville, Virginia. The first part (#7284) was accessioned on September 4, 1963; the second (#7284-a) was accessioned on September 13,1963. Both accessions were made a gift by the owners, Elizabeth and Rebecca Brockenbrough, effective December 31, 1965.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Henry Powell was born on September 6, 1882 to John Henry and Rebecca Leigh Powell. His father was the principal of the Richmond Female Seminary for twenty-six years. Powell was born with musical aptitude and was reported to be singing altos as a baby and writing compositions at age four. He studied music under his sister, Mrs. Smith Brockenbrough, F. C. Hahr, and after graduating from the University of Virginia in 1901, went to Berlin to study under Leschetizky. He also studied composition from Novratil, while he was still in Berlin.
His professional debut as a pianist was in Vienna in 1906. He performed in Berlin in December 1907, Paris in April 1908, and London in May 1908. He went on European tours in 1910 and 1914. He also performed in New York in 1913. His first American tour was in 1916. He also went on a European tour with Walter Damrosch and the New York Symphony Orchestra, playing his own composition, Rhapsodie Negre, in 1920. In 1928 he was on a European and British tour which was supported by the United States government in an effort to improve relations with Britain.
While still performing concerts, Powell spent fifteen years [1932 to 1947] composing his magnum opus, Symphony in A which was successfully played in 1947. John Powell was managed by the National Broadcasting Artist's Service in New York. He married Louise Burleigh, a playwright and artist in her own right in 1928. Powell also taught music at Denver College and was president of the Virginia Music Federation. He also taught piano lessons, gave advice to numerous musicians and composers and mentored Annabel Morris Buchanan, the president of the National Music Federation. He was an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa, Socit Astronomique de France, and the American Institute of Arts and Letters.
Some of Powell's musical works are Sonata Virginianesque, Sonata A Flat, Sonate Noble, Rhapsodie Negre, Natchez-On-the-Hill, Variations and Double-Fugue; Overture: In Old Virginia. Folksongs of John Powell include At the Fair, Hoochee-Coochee Dance, Circassian Beauty, Merry-go-round, Clowns, Snake-Charmer, Banjo-Picker, In the Hammock, Dirge, From a Loved Past, and In the South.
John Powell was a proud Virginian, a southerner and a great pianist who traveled all over the world performing his music. He was passionate about the preservation of folk music and he felt that the music was a genuine remnant of Anglo-Saxon culture. As a boy he was taught that Anglo-Saxons are not musicians and he was determined to prove this untrue by uncovering folk music and ballads belonging to Anglo-Saxons. He also spent his life trying to preserve America as a pure Anglo-Saxon society and was considered the founding father of racial integrity legislation in Virginia. He met with politicians, gave speeches, and proposed ideas for preserving the white race in America.
His work in eugenics began in the early 1920s and he supported racial integrity legislation that passed through the General Assembly of Virginia in 1926. He continued to propose amendments to the legislation and to encourage other states to follow Virginia's racial integrity laws. He promoted Anglo-Saxon Clubs of America and wrote a book, Mongrels in Virginia which expresses his views concerning the importance of keeping the races separate. He worked closely with Earnest Sevier Cox, Madison Grant, Dr. Walter Ashby Plecker, Lothrop Stoddard, H. Norton Mason, Marcus Garvey, and many others in an effort to preserve the white race in America. He edited the writings of his colleagues and had a close relationship with The Richmond-Times-Dispatch. The United States Congress supported equal Constitutional rights for all citizens and Powell's efforts were defeated. Powell died in Richmond, Virginia in 1963, a few years after his wife, Louise Burleigh Powell, had passed away.
Scope and Content
The papers consist chiefly of the correspondence of John Powell, a world-renowned pianist and composer who lived in Richmond and Charlottesville, Virginia from his birth in 1882 until his death in 1963. The collection consists of ca.15,025 items, 45 Hollinger boxes, and 225 linear feet. The correspondence includes letters to John and his wife, Louise Burleigh Powell from 1908 to 1963. There are personal letters to friends in the United States, Germany, Austria, England, and France as well as professional correspondence with music agents and composers in the United States and England. Some of the correspondents are Gamaliel Bradford, Leander January de Bekker, Annabel Morris Buchanan, Harry Flood Byrd, Jr., James Branch Cabell; Joseph Conrad, Francis Warrington Dawson, Lord Dunsany, Mary Johnston, Daniel Gregory Mason, John Lloyd Newcomb; Walter Ashby Plecker, Katherine (Kitty) Buckley Powell, Amelie Rives, Eleanor Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr., Claude Augustus Swanson, and Winston Wilkinson.
Most of the correspondence relates to the provisions needed to give concerts and negotiations between commercial music agents and music clubs. Correspondence also focuses on the discovery of folk songs, requests for Powell to act as a judge in musical contests and Powell's work with many Universities to increase the understanding of folk music. There is also information about Powell's efforts to set up a Music Department at the University of Virginia and a Silver Jubilee concert at Carnegie Hall where the proceeds of Powell's concert are to be donated to the University of Virginia Library for the purchase of letters by Thomas Jefferson and [Joseph] Cabell. There is also a set of stamps from the Charlottesville Apple Festival included in the correspondence from 1953. (Box 18, folder 7)
In addition to correspondence, there are manuscripts relating to John Powell, including articles, and course materials on the history of folk music. He promoted courses on folk music and gave performances to local music clubs all over the country in an attempt to educate the public about this type of music. There are also piano works, such as Dirge, a piano duet by Powell, op. 26, notes about programs, musical scores, reviews of musical compositions, and speeches.
Included in the manuscripts of this collection is a civil war account that was given to John Powell titled, Recollections of a Courier of the Last Ten Days of the Army. It is a first hand account of life on the battlefield in the Civil War and is published in the Confederate Veteran, vol. 27 (1919), page 341.
Other manuscripts include original drafts of plays by Louise Burleigh Powell and musical and drama manuscripts by colleagues of John and Louise Powell. The manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type of material. Following the manuscripts in this collection, is printed material for musical programs.
The Powell collection also has significant correspondence on eugenics and racial integrity. Powell's dedication to folk music was equaled by his passionate interest in maintaining the purity of the Anglo-Saxon race in America. He was very active in establishing Anglo-Saxon Clubs of America and promoting legislation that would keep the races separate. There are articles about eugenics and many letters written to John Powell about racial integrity, including vivid descriptions by his wife, Louise Burleigh Powell, of the racial laws being argued in the courtroom. Powell also collaborated with Marcus Garvey in a movement that tried to colonize African Americans.
Dr. Walter Ashby Plecker, the State Registrar of the Bureau of Vital Statistics in Virginia, shared Powell's passion for racial integrity, and sent copies of all his correspondence concerning racial matters to Powell. Dr. Plecker believed that the Indians had mixed with African Americans and there were no longer any pure Indians in Virginia. He wrote on the back of their birth certificates that they were not Indian. Plecker dedicated his life to preventing African Americans from trying to pass as Indian or White and there are many copies of his letters in the collection.
In addition to the correspondence of John Powell and Dr. Walter Ashby Plecker, there are news clippings from The Richmond Times-Dispatch, The Richmond News Leader, The Daily Progress and several other newspapers about racial integrity and John Powell.
Arrangement
The Papers of John Powell have six series beginning with correspondence in Series I. Most of the correspondence of John and Louise Powell is in chronological order in Subseries A, section number 1. There is a second and smaller section of his correspondence which is in order by topic and consists of business cards, fans, interviews and press releases, personal, and V.I.P. correspondence in Subseries A, section number 2. The correspondence of their colleagues and friends is in Subseries B.
Series II consists of manuscripts of music and plays in topical order by type of material. Subseries A contains manuscripts by John Powell. Subseries B includes manuscripts by other musicians. Subseries C has manuscripts of Louise Burleigh Powell, a playwright. Subseries D contains manuscripts of other playwrights.
Series III includes printed materials about music, such as programs for recitals and news clippings about music. The programs are in order by date and the news clippings are arranged by topic.
Series IV consists of information on eugenics and racial integrity and is single foldered by date. There are four subseries containing information on eugenics. In Subseries A, there are articles and legislation about eugenics. Subseries B has correspondence of John Powell concerning eugenics. Subseries C contains the correspondence of Dr. Walter Ashby Plecker. Subseries D includes news clippings about eugenics.
Series V is a collection of photographs relating to John Powell.
Series VI consists of miscellaneous items, such as biographical information, financial information and papers including memberships and organizations that Powell attended.
Contents List
- Series I.: Correspondence
  - Subseries A.: Correspondence of John and Louise Powell
    - Section 1.: Chronological Correspondence
      Letters are from family, friends, fellow musicians, and business associates to John and Louise Powell concerning music as well as personal information unless otherwise noted. Correspondence of Louise Powell is included as she is a correspondent for John Powell when he is busy or traveling. Boxes 1-25
      - Correspondence. 1888, 6 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
        Letters from Carrie [Williams] and Rebecca [Coleman], sisters of John Powell to their mother and father.
      - Correspondence. 1899, 2 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
        Letters to John Powell from his sisters, parents, and close friends.
      - Correspondence, 1899, 7 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
        Letters to John Powell from his sisters, parents, and close friends. There are also letters from John Powell to his mother and father.
        Correspondents include Bettie P. Brockenbrough and Rebecca Coleman, sisters of John Powell; Rebecca Powell, mother of John Powell; John P. McGuire Jr.
      - Correspondence, 1899, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
        Letters of condolence to John Powell regarding the loss of his father.
        Correspondents include Percy Montague; Nettie Eastman; Kitty [B.P.]; Lavinia E. Curter; Pope Nash; [JCS]; Hallie M. Echols.
      - Correspondence, 1900-1901, 30 items. (Box-folder 1:5-6)
        Letters to John Powell from his mother, sisters, and close friends.
      - Correspondence, 1902, 21 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
        Correspondents include Aunt Eliza Leigh; Henry Leigh; Kitty [B.P.] Lindsay Powers; [Padulary]; [Pa Fritz].
      - Correspondence, 1903, 42 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
        Correspondents include Aunt Eliza Leigh; sisters Carrie Williams and Bettie Brockenbrough; John Powell's mother, Rebecca; [Wheelyman].
      - Correspondence, 1904-1906, 17 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
        Correspondence includes John Powell's nephew; John Powell's sister, Rebecca Coleman; John Powell's mother; Robert Stiles; and a letter of advice on marriage from Helen Gibson Stockdell.
      - Correspondence, 1907, 22 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
        Corresponents include Elizabeth Scarborough; Henry Kohn; Powell's niece, Julia; George Blankenship; D. M. Nordan; Lady Nancy Astor; Francis Warrington Dawson; Powell's sister, Bettie Brockenbrough; E. Claremont, Clarefeilds Operatic and Concert Agents.
      - Correspondents, 1908, 14 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
        Correspondents include Bettie Brockenbrough; Francis Warrington Dawson; E. Claremont; Clarefields; D. M. Nordan.
      - Correspondence, 1909, 25 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
        Correspondents include Paul Petri; James Parker; [H.A. McComas;] Frau Emilie Sigmann; Charlotte Mugdan; [Daisy;] Francis Warrington Dawson; Dr. Ernst Specht; Edna Buckbee; George H. von Lucas; Jeremy Taylor; Angel Bickerdike; [Fannie Marie Cuttenet;] Chappell & Co.; Metzler & Co; A. Z. Mathot.
      - Correspondence, 1910, 62 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Correspondents include Francis Warrington Dawson; Powell's sisters Carrie and Bettie; nephew, John Powell and niece Becca; Edina Bligh; Elizabeth Darling; Fred M. Kirkus; Gret Gatty; Mary Stevens; Novello Davis; Isabel Kirkwood; A. S. Green; Gerard Thorp; Chappell & Co.; Mabel Noble; Joseph Schilbach; Albert Gutman.
      - Correspondence, 1911, 16 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Correspondents include Powell's sister, Bettie Brockenbrough; nephew, John Powell; Arthur Tremble; Fred M. Kirkus; [K. Rothler;] Chappel & Co.; Francis Warrington Dawson.
      - Correspondents, 1912, 8 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Joseph Conrad tells Francis Warrington Daws that he wants to meet Powell.
        Correspondents include R. Rotulan; Francis Warrington Dawson; Betty Brockenbrough; nephews John Powell Williams, Reid Williams and niece Rebecca; John Powell to Mr. Wilstead.
      - Correspondence, 1913, 15 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Correspondents include Christl Kerry; [Riesler;] John Powell's sister, Carrie Williams; Kate Dalliban John; A. Z. Mathot; Ernest Urchs, Steinway & Sons; Sigmeund Spaeth; Mrs. Edmund John; Edward R. Stettinius, Diamond Match Co., with press cuttings; T. W. Lamont, Esq.
      - Correspondence, 1914, 19 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Correspondents include Pritzi Kerry; Dick Obbo; Monica Dailey; Gutman; Rebecca Powell; Francis Warrington Dawson; [Betty] Brockenbrough; Carol Rockwood.
      - Correspondence, 1915, 4 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Correspondents include Francis Neff; Charlie Norman.
      - Correspondence, 1916, 44 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
        Friends congratulate Powell on his success and colleagues want copies of his suite, At the Fair, From the South.
        Correspondents include Mrs. A. J. Ochsner; George Mackenzie; Wilhelm Altman; Bernard Lytton-Bernard; Francis Warrington Dawson; Arthur Foote; Betty Smith Brockenbrough; Louis A. Freedman; Ossip Gabrilowitsch; Harry [Rogers Pratt]; John Hutchinson; Cary Franklin Jacob; Kenneth S. Jones; Fred W. Kirkus; E. H. Manning; Marie W. Motginger; Charlie Norman; James A. Pittman; H. D. Potter; Edward Powers; John W. Frothingham; Randall MacIver; Janet Ramsay; Helen Russell; Minnie D. Sherrill; Bettie Thalhimer Solomon; Jo Clay Stiles; Maud Kraft-Honeyman; Rose L. Sutro; M. Teresa Thompson; Mabell Tuttle; Ernest Urchs; Pace Alro; Karl Zingen; Pritzi Kerry.
      - Correspondence, 1916-1922, 51 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
        Louise Powell. Lord Dunsany's secretary writes to Louise Burleigh that Lord Dunsany cannot answer her letter for awhile because he is shooting in North Africa.
        Correspondents include Louise Burleigh [Powell] to John Powell; Louise Burleigh [Powell] to Augustine Duncan; Jacob Altschuler; Alexander Bakshy; Charles S. [Berks]; Gamaliel Bradford; Clarence Boykin; Alice Brown; Percy J. Burrell; W. B. Cridlin, Virginia Historical Pageant Association; Augustine Duncan; Lord Dunsany; W. M. Forrest; Henry F. Gilbert; Susan Glaspall; George [Pullen Jackson]; L. M. Hallowes; Brockenbrough Lamb; George Le Soir; Corrine Melchers; Harold Paget; [Emma Kerry;] Henriette Paskar; James B. Pinker; Margaret Rhodes; Phyllis M. Scott, secretary, Schuster Martin School; T. S. Settle; R. L. Giffin; Francis Warrington Dawson; Wanda B. Clifton; Virginia Blackwell; Bertha Iles; Betty Williamson.
      - Correspondence, 1917, 33 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
        Leander January de Bekker writes to John Powell's sister that he enjoys Powell's compositions. Some upcoming concerts are Grand Rapids, Michigan; John Powell Fugue at Randolph Macon, Lynchburg, Virginia; Sweetbriar College, Lynchburg, Virginia; Averett College, Danville, Virginia; Chicago, Illinois; Sonata E Flat at Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Birmingham, Alabama. Powell also performs Liszt Hungarian Fantasia, Liszt A Major and Beethoven Sonata. Effrem Zimbalist requests the use of the piano part of Powell's violin sonata.
        Some correspondents include Frederick Alexander; Carl Andersch; T. Archibald Cary; E. Adams; Arthur Foote; Phyllis Brand; Mrs. Samuel W. Cooper; Leander January de Bekker to Mrs. [Carrie] Williams; George Engles; John W. Frothingham; Winfried Garlitt; Fred M. Kirkus; Louise C. Leigh; Nancy G. Leigh; William Morrow; Agnes Terrell; M. C. Thompson; Vera Bull Hull; Harriette Weber; Effrem Zimbalist; Arnaud Lachmund; J. Pizzarello; Frederick A. Stokes Company; L. Mary Willis; Betty Brockenbrough
      - Correspondence, 1918, 59 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
        Leander January de Bekker would like to meet John Powell. Winton & Livingston become Powell's manager because his old manager, Frothingham, Inc. is no longer arranging concerts due to the war. Alfreda Peel sends a collection of folksongs; Powell performs Grieg Sonata at Carnegie Hall; Rhapsodie Negre and At the Fair in Detroit, Michigan; Other upcoming concerts include The Metropolitan; Rhapsodie Negre at Norfolk, Connecticut; Toledo, Ohio; Cleveland, Ohio; Chattanooga, Tennessee; Atlanta, Georgia; Scranton, Pennsylvania; Erie, Pennsylvania. There is also correspondence about a petition for a National Conservancy of Music. G. Schirmer accepts Powell's Sonata Virginianesque.
        Correspondents include Mary Albro; W. Sanford Beasley; Leander January de Bekker; M. Benmosche; Zarh Myron Bickford; Effie Branch; Vera Hull Bull; Winton and Livingston; Newton J. Corey; Harry Cyphers; Walter Damrosch; Lily Hammerschlay; Florence D. Heguenbourg; Charles D. Isaacson, The Globe; Arnaud Lachmund; Marjorie G. Lachmund; Felix F. Leifels; Andrew J. Montague, petition for National Conservatory of Music; Mary M. Montague; Alfreda M. Peel; G. Schirmer, Inc.; Alice Sheldon; Josef Stransky, Conductor, The Philharmonic Society of New York; M. Teresa Thompson; Josephine Thorp; Mabell Tuttle; Alice Dukes; Ernest Urchs; Victor C. Winton.
      - Correspondence, 1919, 63 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
        The Russian Symphony Society is in an unfortunate predicament that creates financial stress for Modest Altschuler; Sergei Rachmaninoff is mentioned in the letter. David Guion writes about his folksongs, Darkey Spirituals, Texas Fox-Trot, and Turkey in the Straw. Christl and Emma Kerry, Austrian friends of John Powell thank him for his effort in writing to the United States Government asking for the return of their money that was taken from them during the war.
        Correspondents include Marion Achsner; W. F. Augustine; Bernard Lytton-Bernard; Mary Kennedy Boone; George B. Chadwick; W. H. Cloudman; Francis Warrington Dawson; Becca Virginia Frank; Charles T. Griffes; David W. Guion; Henry Hadley; George Harris, Jr.; Christine Herrish; Stockton Holsted; Ernest Hutcheson; Charles D. Isaacson; N. V. Joseph; Arthur Judson; Christl Kerry; Daniel Gregory Mason; Daniel Mayer; Frank J. O'Hara; George Foster Peabody; Margaret Poole; Janet Ramsay; B. Scott; Bula Ray Shull; [Betty Smith Brockenbrough]; Carl Stoeckel; Rose L. Sutro; Anne Tucker; Burnet C. Tuthill; Mabell Tuttle; C. G. J. Volkert; V. C. Winton; Yvonne [de Treville].
      - Correspondence, 1920 January-May, 45 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
        Powell accepts an offer to play in Walter Damrosch's Orchestra on tour in Europe. Concerts on his return from the tour include Jamestown, North Carolina; St. Mary's School, Raleigh, North Carolina; State Normal School, Harrisonburg, Virginia; Pittsfield, Massachusetts; Dayton, Ohio.
        Correspondents include Carl Andersch; Lillie d'Angelo Bergh; Bernard Lytton-Bernard; Francis L. Burke; Louise Burleigh [Powell]; W. H. Cloudman, Winton & Livingston; Harry Cypher, Detroit Symphony Orchestra; Francis Warrington Dawson; Alice Dukes; Mrs. Archibald Freer; Abbie H. C. Finck; A. B. Guigon, Attorney; George Harris, Jr. Alpha Delta Club; Elizabeth Butler Howry; Lou Belle C. Jones; Christl Kerry; Matsukhi Kerry; Blanche Collins Krise; Gardner Lamsor; Mr. and Mrs. Chauncey Moon; Harold Morris, Pianist-Composer; Adelaide O'Brien; Clarendon H. Pfeiffer, The Aeolian Company; Percy Rector Stephens; William Burnet Tuthill, Society for the Publication of American Music; William Treat Upton; A. A. Van de Mark; Victor C. Winton, Winton & Livingston
      - Correspondence, 1920 June-December, 45 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
        John Powell's schedule for upcoming concerts includes Norfolk, Virginia; Roanoke, Virginia; Radford, Virginia; Bradford, Pennsylvania; Worcester, Massachusetts; Henderson, North Carolina; Hollins, Virginia; Oswego, New York, Greensboro, North Carolina; New Rochelle, New York.
        Correspondents include Maria Blair; Phyllis Windsor Clive; Jessie Conrad; M. S. Quinton Downer; Walter Galz; Ellen Glasgow; George Harris, Jr., Alpha Delta Club; Josephine S. Sauier; Marie Kieckhoefer; Music League of America; Daniel Gregory Mason; Rosa Tucker Mason; Charles Henry Meltzer; Grace Halsey Mills; Margaret C. [Setchell]; Maud Christian Sherwood; Mrs. Claude L. Steele, National Federation of Music Clubs; Dolly [Stevens]; John Sutro; H. F. Truman, National Concerts; C. G. J. Volkert; Winston & Livingston.
        Letters from Louise Burleigh [Powell] to John Powell mention Amélie and Pierre [Troubetzkoy,] James Branch Cabell and Joseph and Jessie Conrad.
      - Correspondence, 1921 January-August, 27 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
        George P. Baker requests that Powell write music for a Robert Frost poem to be played at the Plymouth Pageant; Powell completes his Overture, In Old Virginia.
        Correspondents include E. Baker; George P. Baker; Betty Barker; Walter Dabney Blair; Wade R. Brown; Loudon Charlton; Chalmers Clifton; James J. Deck; Stanislao Gallo; C. T. Herrick; Basset W. Hough; Daniel Gregory Mason; Scratch W. Snuker; Carl Stoeckel; Selma Weirs; Raymond B. Williams.
      - Correspondence, September-December 1921, 46 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
        Friends write to Powell for advice or favors. Students request piano lessons. Eva Chataice asks Powell to give an evening lecture on folk music to benefit the American branch of the Comite de l'Esperance in raising funds for the reconstruction of France. Upcoming concerts are in Anderson, South Carolina; Cleveland, Ohio; Amherst, Massachusetts, and Greenfield, Massachusetts.